foreign
[Music]
over the past 20 years or so big Pharma
has invested more than a half trillion
dollars into dementia treatment research
but so far it's a little avail
in light of this many have turned to
supplements an AARP commission survey
found that 36 of those 74 years and
older take a supplement for brain health
to the tune of billions of dollars a
year the most commonly marketed brain
supplement was one I'd frankly never
heard of before Prevagen
Prevagen contains a protein derived from
a luminescent jellyfish the company
claims has been clinically shown to
improve memory according to the company
website a landmark double-blind and
placebo-controlled trial demonstrated
Prevagen improved short-term memory
learning and delayed recall over 90 days
but when you actually pull up the study
not only did Prevagen failed to improve
memory learning or recall over Placebo
it failed to show a significant
Improvement in any of the nine measured
cognitive tasks tested as an inquiry
into Prevagen published by the Center
for Science in the public interest was
titled how can this memory supplement
flunk its one trial and still be
advertised as effective and not just as
effective but the number one pharmacist
recommended brand considering the lack
of sound clinical evidence how is that
possible presumably they're just as
blitzed with the same kind of
advertising as everyone else
it's no surprise the supplement didn't
do anything since the company's own
study showed the jellyfish protein was
rapidly digested by stomach enzymes of
course that didn't stop them from raking
in more than 20 million dollars a year
claiming the market is a Prevagen preyed
on the fears of older consumers
experiencing age-related memory loss the
Federal Trade Commission and New York
State's Attorney General filed a
consumer protection complaint charging
the company with making false and
unsubstantiated claims the AARP weighed
in accusing the company of deceiving
millions of Aging Americans
in a move straight out of the big form
of educanumab Playbook the company went
back and conducted more than 30 post-hoc
analyzes of the data and found a few
positive findings on a few tasks for
some subgroups this cherry picking of
subgroups after the fact is a classic
example of manipulation sometimes called
P hacking or data dredging that can be
described as placing a bet on horse
after watching the race the makers of
Prevagen settled a class action lawsuit
in 2020 with the FTC over deceptive
business practices and false advertising
remarkably though the settlement allows
them to continue to Market it with a
court-approved disclaimer the claims are
based on a clinical study of subgroups
of individuals but with the amount of
slicing and dicing of data they did the
chances of finding at least one false
positive was estimated at 80 percent
Prevagen maybe more than just a waste of
money the manufacturer was cited for
failing to report more than a thousand
Adverse Events related by consumers to
the Food and Drug Administration
Regulators can't have it both ways
though I mean if the jellyfish protein
is digested away how can impose a safety
risk because dietary supplements are too
often adulterated with contaminants FDA
inspectors specifically cited prevagen's
manufacturing facilities for
objectionable conditions or practices
a 2019 survey by Pew found that more
than half believed that the Food and
Drug Administration requires supplements
to be tested for safety but that isn't
true
one study of 24 supplements sold as
cognitive performance boosters found
that most claimed an ingredient on the
label that wasn't actually in the
supplement and worse 38 contained
ingredients not allowed in supplements
like prohibited drugs another study that
doesn't so-called brain health
supplements similarly found 8 out of 12
were misbranded missing an ingredient
promised on the label and 10 out of 12
were deemed adultery containing unlisted
compounds for example caffeine and a
product that explicitly highlighted all
caps decaffeinated on the label only one
out of 12 was certified to contain what
it said it did the bottom line for
Prevagen there is no acceptable evidence
that it's effective patients should be
advised not to take it
[Music]
thank you